

Todd M. Ellis

DATA ANALYST & STATISTICAL PROGRAMMER

Greater Hobart Region, Tasmania, Australia April 2023

□+61 466 683 552 | ▼toddellis.wa@gmail.com | ○ 0000-0002-4410-8676 | ☑ q6vTAroAAAAJ | ☑ Todd-Ellis-4 |

otoddellis | tmichaelellis

PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY.

I'm a data analyst and scientist with a background in forest ecology, physical geography, and higher education. I've worked as an analyst in a wide variety of laboratory, field, and office settings across the United States and Australia. Over the course of my career, I've developed novel mathematical tools and statistical models; maintained relational databases and statistical packages used for conducting data analysis and producing standardized reports; trained countless staff, students, and volunteers; and managed complex and critical projects. My research has been published in high-impact, peer-reviewed journals, and I'm also skilled at conveying complex data and information to both casual and experienced stakeholders.

EDUCATION

Doctor of Philosophy, Biological Sciences

Sandy Bay, TAS, Australia

University of Tasmania 2019 - present

- · Dissertation: Dynamic mapping and analysis of New South Wales fire regimes: Past, present, and future
- Supervisors: Drs. Grant J. Williamson and David M.J.S. Bowman

Master of Science, Geography

Bellingham, WA, USA

WESTERN WASHINGTON UNIVERSITY

2013 - 2016

- Thesis: Climatic drivers of western spruce budworm outbreaks in the Okanogan Highlands
- · Supervisor: Dr. Aquila Flower

Bachelor of Science, Physical Geography / Geology

San Marcos, TX, USA

TEXAS STATE UNIVERSITY

2007 - 2012

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Data Insights Analyst Sandy Bay, TAS, Australia

University of Tasmania: Division of Future Students (full-time)

2023-01 - present

- Developing novel student admissions tools and processes using novel data and modelling
- · Leading development and modelling on higher education programs actively improving equity of access for potential applicants
- Providing insights and consulting to university stakeholders across the institution

Adjunct Researcher Sandy Bay, TAS, Australia

University of Tasmania: College of Sciences and Engineering (full-time)

2019-09 - 2023-03

- Developed complex data-processing and analysis pipelines using high-performance computing and big data
- · Oversaw multi-year projet design and implementation addressing wildfire and global climate change challenges
- Managed custom platform for interactive web-mapping, on-the-fly statistical analyses, and novel data visualisation
- · Collaborated with national and international research teams tackling climate change risk and mitigation

Data Analyst Sandy Bay, TAS, Australia

University of Tasmania: Division of Future Students (part-time / full-time)

2021-02 - 2023-01

- Developed statistical models and tools for meeting target university milestones
- Managed design and implementation of broad-scale university ML models for directing future university marketing, funding, and course creation
- Designed and implemented programming and data analytics training seminars for institution staff
- Oversaw development of internal reporting and statistical packages
- Processed, analysed and reported data to promote and review university programs

Sustainability Analyst

Sandy Bay, TAS, Australia

2019-10 - 2021-02

University of Tasmania: Division of Future Students (casual)

- Processed, analysed, and reported data to promote and review institution programmes
- Developed pipelines for automating data cleaning and collation
- Prepared data and briefings for global institution rankings
- Promoted nation-wide sustainability targets using data dashboards and reports

Data & GIS Analyst Austin, TX, USA

APEX SYSTEMS: APPLE, INC. (CONTRACT) 2018-12 - 2019-05

- · Developed and standardised data-processing methods for vector and multispectral raster datasets
- Managed and processed corporate GIS databases using data-driven software and programming languages
- · Prepared statistical summaries, models, and analytical reports
- · Led research and development projects to define novel methodologies for geospatial data
- Collaboratd with a global network of analysts and technicians

Faculty Research Assistant

Wenatchee, WA, USA

2017-11 - 2018-06

OREGON STATE UNIVERSITY: USDA FOREST SERVICE FORESTRY SCIENCES LABORATORY (CONTRACT)

- Converted complex data and findings into academic and government reports
- Developed explanatory models for sustainable forest management under climate change
- Created and maintained relational databases for government research
- Gathered and analysed ecological data using statistical software

Biological Science Technician II

Ridgefield, WA, USA

2017-08 - 2017-11

WASHINGTON DEPARTMENT OF FISH AND WILDLIFE: REGION 5 (CONTRACT)

- Applied QA/QC to develop electronic biological data collection system and relational database
- Analysed biological fisheries data for state government research reporting
- · Collected and recorded biological data for government research and both commercial and tribal fisheries
- · Designed, built, and maintained department, fisheries, and commercial research equipment
- · Conducted outreach to the public, providing information on fisheries research, management principles, and local regulations
- Monitord critical fish migrations using DNA sampling and the PTAGIS coordination project
- · Received training in fish, plant, and organism identification, government safety procedures, boat operation, and defensive driving

Substitute Teacher Kelso, WA, USA

KELSO SCHOOL DISTRICT: BEACON HILL ELEMENTARY SCHOOL (CASUAL)

2017-01 - 2017-08

- Taught a variety of classrooms, with a focus on K-5 primary education, special education, and LAP classrooms using specialised learning plans
- · Engaged young students with an interest in scientific research, giving special outreach presentations
- Helped integrate and refine special education lesson plans as an instructional assistant

Graduate Teaching Assistant

Bellingham, WA, USA

WESTERN WASHINGTON UNIVERSITY: HUXLEY COLLEGE OF THE ENVIRONMENT (FULL-TIME)

2013-08 - 2016-06

- Conceptualised, developed, and published novel dendroecological research
- Presented research findings at national academic conferences
- · Coordinated and taught laboratory classrooms for analytical GIS, remote sensing, and research methodology
- Trained and led teams of students in the safe use of field and laboratory equipment in inclement weather and rough terrain
- Scripted statistical methods for identifying complex ecological and climatological relationships
- Presided over and maintained the Huxley Tree Ring Laboratory
- Coordinated international travel and classrooms for students and participating agencies
- · Edited and performed technical reviews of student research papers at the developmental, substantive, and line level
- Classes taught: Remote Sensing (ESCI 442), Introduction to GIS (ENVS 320), Computer Cartography (ENVS 321), Research and Writing (ENVS 319), Environmental Data and Information (ENVS 201), Environmental History and Ethics (ENVS 305), Physical Geography (ENVS 203), the Soil Environment and Landscapes (ENVS 427), Water Resources (ENVS 427), Agroecology and Sustainable Agriculture (ENVS 410), Food Cultures of Italy (ENVS 497), and Ecogastronomy (ENVS 110)

Research Engineer Austin, TX, USA

THE UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS AT AUSTIN: TEXAS NATURAL SCIENCE CENTER (CONTRACT)

2013-04 - 2013-08

- Compiled, georeferences, and managed academic collections and geospatial databaes
- Contributed historial species range data to statewide virtual biodiversity museum
- · Reconstructed historical biodata collections and events

Trail Management Intern

Angeles National Forest, CA, USA

STUDENT CONSERVATION ASSOCIATION: USDA FOREST SERVICE, REIGON 5 (INTERNSHIP)

2013-01 - 2013-04

- Co-managed Trails Assessment and Conditions Survey (TrACS) team
- Conducted detailed survey of fire damage to public roads and trail systems
- Assisted in infrastructure restoration projects to maximise public access benefits
- · Received national government-sponsored training in defensive driving

Laboratory Assistant Austin, TX, USA

THE UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS AT AUSTIN: TEXAS NATUAL SCIENCE CENTER (INTERNSHIP)

2012-08 - 2013-01

- Catalogued, conserved, photographed, and archived acadmic fish and fossils collections
- Maintained and updated relational database management system for institution collections
- Trained volunteers and students in laboratory safety and inventory procedures

Laboratory Assistant San Marcos, TX, USA

2012-08 - 2012-12

TEXAS STATE UNIVERSITY: DEPARTMENT OF GEOGRAPHY (INTERNSHIP)

- · Established geology and palaeontology laboratories for the university
- Prepared vertebrate fossils for laboratory use and public display
- Trained volunteers in laboratory procedures and sample preparation techniques
- Organised and led field exercises for sample collections and cleanings
- Captured and processed ichnological and palaeontological data using Structure from Motion
- Curated departmental fossils and rock collections

VOLUNTEER EXPERIENCE

Foster Parent Hobart, TAS, Australia

TEN LIVES CAT CENTRE 2020-05 - present

Animal Handler New Braunfels, TX, USA

HUMANE SOCIETY OF THE NEW BRAUNFELS AREA 2018-08 - 2019-01

Wenatchee, WA, USA WENATCHEE VALLEY HUMANE SOCIETY 2018-03 - 2018-08

Technology Tutor Wenatchee, WA, USA

NORTH CENTRAL REGIONAL LIBRARY 2018-01 - 2018-08

Geographic Information Systems Technician Portland, OR, USA PORTLAND STATE UNIVERSITY 2017-01 - 2017-11

Assistant Librarian Kelso, WA, USA

BEACON HILL ELEMENTARY SCHOOL 2017-01 - 2017-11

Technology Tutor Bellingham, WA, USA

BELLINGHAM PUBLIC LIBRARY 2014-07 - 2016-08

Laboratory Assistant Austin, TX, USA

THE UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS AT AUSTIN 2012-01 - 2012-07

Laboratory Assistant San Marcos, TX, USA TEXAS STATE UNIVERSITY 2011-03 - 2012-07

PUBLICATIONS

Animal Handler

JOURNAL ARTICLES

Double-differenced dNBR: Combining MODIS and Landsat imagery to map fine-grained fire mosaics in lowland Eucalyptus savanna in Kakadu National Park, northern Australia

Fire. https://doi.org/10.3390/fire5050160

2022-02 Global increase in wildfire risk due to climate-driven declines in fuel moisture

Global Change Biology. https://doi.org/10.1111/gcb.16006

A multicentury dendrochronological reconstruction of western spruce budworm outbreaks in the 2017-09 Okanogan Highlands, northeastern Washington

Canadian Journal of Forest Research. https://doi.org/10.1139/cjfr-2016-0399

THESES

2016-06 Climatic Drivers of Western Spruce Budworm Outbreaks in the Okanogan Highlands

Western Washington University. https://doi.org/10.25710/d4xw-5825

OPEN-ACCESS DATA

Double-differenced dNBR: Combining MODIS and Landsat imagery to map fine-grained fire mosaics in 2022-10 lowland Eucalyptus savanna in Kakadu National Park, northern Australia

figshare. https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.21259524

2021-11 Global ERA5 fuel moisture trends 1979 - 2019

figshare. https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.16794727

SOFTWARF

2021-11 utaspptx: Simple methods for producing themed reports and presentations in Microsoft Office software GitHub. private
 2021-08 miao: Custom exploratory data analysis and statistical tools
 GitHub. https://github.com/toddellis/miao
 2021-05 utastoolkit: Tools for accessing and reporting internal University data from the Enterprise Data Warehouse GitHub. private

CONSULTING

RESEARCH

2020-08 Predicting fire behaviour using historical satellite imagery
Frontier Development Lab

2019-06 Post-fire logging effects on reburn severity
USDA Forest Service

2018-08 Restoration treatment effects on ponderosa pine growth sensitivity to climate
USDA Forest Service

MANUSCRIPT REVIEWER

Earth's Future (since 2022-09)

Fire Ecology (since 2019-01)

Global Change Biology (since 2022-10)

New Phytologist (since 2022-11)

OUTREACH_

CONFERENCES AND PRESENTATIONS

2022-12	Removing Barriers and transforming access to tertiary education: The Schools Recommendation Program in Tasmania	Macquarie Park,
	Australasian Association for Institutional Research Forum 2022	NSW
2022-09	Schools Recommendation Program Overview	Sandy Bay, TAS
	University of Tasmania Lunch & Learn	Sullay Bay, 1AS
2022-06	Dynamic mapping and analysis of fire regimes, past, present, and future	Wollongong, NSW
	Bushfire Risk Management Research Hub Showcase 2022 (<u>poster</u>)	
2022-02	Intro to sentiment analysis in R	Sandy Bay, TAS
	University of Tasmania Lunch & Learn	
2021-10	Tasmanian Analytics Project	Sandy Bay, TAS
	University of Tasmania and Department of Education Lunch & Learn	
2021-05	Fuel moisture trend tool	Wollongong, NSW
	Bushfire Risk Management Research Hub Researchers' Meeting 2021 (<u>poster</u>)	
2020-03	Changes in moisture availability drive fire risk	Wollongong, NSW
	Bushfire Risk Management Research Hub Researchers' Meeting 2020 (<u>presentation</u>)	
2016-04	Controlling factors of spruce budworm outbreaks in the Okanogan Highlands	San Francisco, CA
	American Association of Geographers Annual Meeting 2016 (presentation)	
2014-07	Climate responses of <i>Pseudotsuga menziesii</i> and <i>Pinus flexilis</i> in the Greater Yellowstone (USA)	Cody, WY
	North American Dendroecological Fieldweek 2014 (<u>presentation</u>)	
2014-04	Perceptions of risk in Bellingham, Washington	Seattle, WA
	Association of Washington Geographers Spring Meeting 2014	

PRESS

2021-10 **Bushfire research team awarded prestigious Eureka Prize**University of Tasmania (<u>article</u>)

COURSEWORK

2020-07	Dynamic mapping and analysis of New South Wales fire regimes: Past, present and future University of Tasmania Graduate Seminars	Sandy Bay, TAS		
2016-06	Climatic Drivers of western spruce budworm outbreaks in the Okanogan Highlands			
	Western Washington University Graduate Defense (presentation)	Bellingham, WA		
2014-05	Controlling factors of spruce budworm outbreaks in the Okanogan Highlands			
	Western Washington University Graduate Seminars	Bellingham, WA		
2014-05	Mapping alpine treeline: A comparative analysis of Structure-from-Motion and LiDAR techniques using digital aerial imagery	Bellingham, WA		
	Western Washington University EGEO 504: Geographic Methods & Techniques (presentation)			
2013-12	Biogeographic implications of Structure-from-Motion imagery	Dellingham 14/4		
	Western Washington University EGEO 501: History and Philosophy of Geography (paper)	Bellingham, WA		
2012-05	Wildfire hazard data for the Yellowstone National Park Ecosystem: 1987-1988	Can Marraca TV		
	Texas State University GEO 4412: Digital Remote Sensing (presentation)	San Marcos, TX		
2012-04	Cretaceous-aged fossiliferous outcrops of the Big Bend region	- 44		
	Texas State University GEO 4310: Regional Field Studies (paper)	San Marcos, TX		
2011-12	Predator-prey relations in the Greater Yellowstone Ecosystem			
	Texas State University GEO 4316: Landscape Biogeography (presentation)	San Marcos, TX		
HONOURS				
AWARDS				
2022-11	Future Students Staff Excellence 2022 Sustainability Award			
	University of Tasmania	AUD\$50		
2021-10	NSW Environment, Energy and Science (DPIE) Eureka Prize for Applied Environmental Research			
	Australian Museum	AUD\$10,000		
2021-09	Future Students Staff Excellence 2021 Sustainability Award			
	University of Tasmania			
2021-08	Certifi-Cat of Appreciation			
	Ten Lives Cat Centre			
2018-06	Best Fish and Wildlife Science			
	Washington Department of Fish and Wildlife			
2017-10	Conservation Award			
2011 10	Washington Department of Fish and Wildlife			
2014-05	Award for Outstanding Poster Presentation by a Graduate Student			
2014 03	Association of Washington Geographers	USD\$125		
0044170				
GRANTS	AND SCHOLARSHIPS			
2020-08	Bushfire Data Quest 2020	AUD¢1 000		
	Frontier Development Lab	AUD\$1,000		
2019-09	Tasmania Graduate Research Scholarship (3.5x)			
	NSW Bushfire Risk Management Research Hub	AUD\$28,000 p.a.		
2019-09	NSW Bushfire Risk Management Research Hub Top-Up (3.5x)			
	NSW Bushfire Risk Management Research Hub	AUD\$5,000 p.a.		
2016-04	Dean and Sandy Blinn Travel and Research Fund			
	Western Washington University	USD\$450		
2016-04	Dean's Fund for Sustainability Studies			
	Western Washington University	USD\$500		
2014-07	North American Dendroecological Fieldweek research fellowship			
	North American Dendroecological Fieldweek	USD\$3,000		
	0.000			